let's move now to inter-process
communication
the example i made with google chrome is
just one
of many examples you can make about why
processes
need to communicate between them in
google chrome you have tabs each tab is
a process
but you have dedicated processes for
instance to render
the html text of each page and in that
case
the renderer and each tab will
communicate will
need to communicate now the operating
system
allows processes provides let's say a
functionality that allows processes to
communicate
there can be different reasons
information sharing computation speed up
modularity and so on
there are two main ways in which two
processes can communicate
they can share memory or they can
exchange messages
when you exchange message you basically
rely on the operating system to maintain
the communication channel
okay while when you
rely on shared memory you take care of
the communication yourself
in between the processes without
involving the
operating system
independently of which one of the two
methods
you use you have always the
producer consumer problem when you have
communication between processes
and it's about decisions you have to
take
about the modes in which the different
processes will
communicate okay you can either go for
an unbounded buffer
so you can prevent putting a practical
limit on the size of the buffer
but then you need to make sure that
the producer will not keep adding stuff
if the
receiver the reader cannot keep up at
the same speed at which the messages are
being sent
or you need to put a bounded buffer
which will help in stopping the producer
if a maximum number of messages that
still have to be read
or retrieved still existing between the
the two processes if we look a bit
better here
so with shared memory
you create a common space between two
processes
and you can directly exchange messages
without relying on the operating system
it's faster because you don't have to
send a message to the operating system
store it somewhere
at the operating system level and then
wait for the operating system to deliver
this message to
the other process but on the other end
it's more complicated to synchronize
you need to make sure that for instance
was to read a certain value does not
read
the value before it has been completely
written by
us to write a value
or that a process does not delete a
certain value
if that could be uh critical afterwards
and so on so the synchronization needs
to be handled
by the processes themselves
on the other hand if you use
message passing that is managed directly
by
the operating system it might perform
not as good as the shared memory but on
the other end
it becomes way simpler to
let's say maintain at least from the
perspective of the process
because you don't need to synchronize
processes
yourself you can rely on the operating
system
this does not mean that this is simpler
okay the
especially if you look at this from the
operating system point of view
there are a lot of issues that you have
to take into
account how to establish the links how
to
create let's say communication channels
that could be shared
among more than two uh processes for
resistance and so on and so forth
okay now we're going to look at a
specific example of
inter-process communication with message
passing maintained by the operating
system